Hello, everyone, and welcome back to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎回到EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
And my name is Catherine, and we've got a great lesson for you today.
我是Catherine，今天我们为大家准备了一堂很棒的课。
What level is this, Marco?
Marco，这课是什么级别的？
This is an elementary lesson, and we're going to be touching one of these medical topics.
这是初级课程，我们会涉及一个医疗话题。
Today we're going to talk about chickenpox.
今天我们要聊聊水痘。
Oh, gosh, I hated the chickenpox.
哦，天哪，我讨厌水痘。
They're horrible, and they itch, and you can't do anything about it, and your parents say,
它们很可怕，还痒，你什么也做不了，你父母会说，
don't scratch.
别挠。
Right.
对。
So chickenpox is an illness that you get usually as a child, and what happens is you start
水痘是一种通常小时候得的病，症状是身上开始
getting these little red dots all over your body, like little mosquito bites.
出现这些小红点，像蚊子包一样。
Exactly, and they come all over your body, arms, legs, face, and you can only get this
没错，它们遍布全身，胳膊、腿、脸，而且这种病你只能得一次，
disease once, unless maybe you didn't really get it too seriously.
除非你之前得得不严重。
So most people get this when they're children.
所以大多数人小时候得这个病。
Exactly, and what makes you very uncomfortable when you get chickenpox, as you said, it's
对，而且得水痘时最难受的，就像你说的，是
these little red dots, they itch, just like mosquito bites, but you can't scratch because
这些小红点，它们痒，就像蚊子包，但你不能挠，因为
if you do, then your skin gets like marked, right?
如果挠了，皮肤就会留下印记，对吧？
You have like stains.
会留下斑点。
Forever.
永远。
Forever, like scars.
永远，像疤痕一样。
So it's best not to scratch, and that's what we're going to talk about today.
所以最好别挠，这就是我们今天要聊的内容。
Somebody has the chickenpox.
有人得了水痘。
So let's listen to our dialogue for the first time, and then we'll be right back.
我们先听一遍对话，然后马上回来。
What's wrong with you?
你怎么了？
Why are you scratching so much?
你怎么挠个不停？
I feel itchy.
我觉得痒。
I can't stand it anymore.
我受不了了。
I think I may be coming down with something.
我觉得我可能生病了。
I feel lightheaded and weak.
我头晕又虚弱。
Let me have a look.
让我看看。
Whoa, get away from me.
哇，离我远点。
What's wrong?
怎么了？
I think you have chickenpox.
我觉得你得了水痘。
I don't know.
我不知道。
I think I have chickenpox.
我觉得我得了水痘。
I don't know.
我不知道。
I think I have chickenpox.
我觉得我得了水痘。
I don't know.
我不知道。
I think I have chickenpox.
我觉得我得了水痘。
I don't know.
我不知道。
I think I have chickenpox.
我想我得了水痘。
I'm going to watch it.
我要去看它。
I'm really curious.
我真的很好奇。
What's that on your hand?
你手上那是什么？
I forget it's golden.
我忘了它是金色的。
I think it's golden.
我觉得它是金色的。
I'm getting stiffer and stiffer.
我越来越僵硬了。
Stiff?
僵硬？
I'm really going to get the chicken or chickenpox.
我真的要去弄鸡或水痘。
I don't know, it's not chicken or things.
我不知道，不是鸡或什么东西。
What is it, it's like...
那是什么，就像...
Alright, we're back, so I think this kid does have the chicken pox.
好了，我们回来了，所以我觉得这个孩子确实得了水痘。
Definitely, and well, he's got a funny solution for it.
没错，而且他有个有趣的解决办法。
But before we get there, we've got a lot of great medical words and just basic body words
但在那之前，我们今天在“语言精华”环节为你准备了很多很棒的和医疗相关的词汇以及基本的身体词汇。
for you in today's Language Takeaway.
语言精华。
Language Takeaway.
Alright, so let's start with our first word.
好了，让我们从第一个词开始。
He mentioned that he felt itchy.
他提到他感觉痒。
I feel itchy.
我感觉痒。
Itchy.
痒。
Okay, this is often confused even among children who are native speakers of English.
好的，这个词即使在以英语为母语的孩子中也经常被混淆。
There are two words, to itch and to scratch.
有两个词：痒和抓。
But this person is itchy, so it means that your skin, you want to scratch it.
但这个人感觉痒，意思是你的皮肤让你想抓它。
It's maybe uncomfortable.
可能有点不舒服。
Like a mosquito bite is itchy.
比如蚊子叮咬会痒。
Okay, so itchy would be the adjective, right?
好的，所以“痒”是形容词，对吧？
To the noun, an itch.
名词是“痒感”。
So if you have an itch, you feel itchy, right?
所以如果你有痒感，你会感觉痒，对吧？
Exactly.
没错。
So, and that's when you scratch.
所以，那就是你抓的时候。
Alright so he feels itchy and he also felt a little bit lightheaded.
好的，所以他感觉痒，还感觉有点头晕。
Okay, so you know the word head, you know the word light.
好的，你知道“头”这个词，也知道“轻”这个词。
So here we have a person who feels lightheaded.
这里我们有一个感觉头晕的人。
It means that you kind of feel a little bit strange and your head is a little bit, well,
意思是你感觉有点奇怪，你的头有点，嗯，
what's a good word to describe it?
用什么词来形容好呢？
Like dizzy.
像眩晕。
Yeah, almost dizzy or faint.
是的，差不多是眩晕或昏厥。
Right.
对。
So, you usually feel a little bit weak.
所以，你通常会感觉有点虚弱。
You don't really feel very well.
你确实感觉不太舒服。
Your head is lightheaded.
你的头有点晕。
The complete opposite of having a headache, right?
这和头痛完全相反，对吧？
Exactly.
没错。
Okay, and well then the girl got scared and she said, get away, you are contagious.
好的，然后那个女孩吓坏了，她说：“走开，你会传染的。”
Oh gosh, now this is a dangerous one.
哦天哪，这可是个危险的词。
Someone who is contagious can pass their illness to someone else.
传染性的人可以把他们的疾病传给其他人。
So for example, the flu is very contagious and if I have the flu, Marco doesn't want
比如，流感传染性很强，如果我得了流感，马可不想
me to, you know, come over and touch all of his stuff and sneeze and cough into his food.
让我靠近，碰他的东西，或者对着他的食物打喷嚏和咳嗽。
Right, exactly.
对，没错。
So that's contagious.
所以这就是传染性。
It's an adjective and that means that you easily pass your illness to another person.
它是一个形容词，意思是你很容易把疾病传给另一个人。
Exactly.
没错。
Alright, so why don't we take a look at a couple of different examples using this word
好的，那我们来看看几个用这个词
contagious.
“传染性”的例子。
Example one.
例子一。
Don't get near me.
别靠近我。
Chicken pox are very contagious.
水痘传染性很强。
Example two.
例子二。
The sickness that is going around the office is very contagious.
办公室里流行的这种病传染性很强。
Example three.
例子三。
H1N1 flu is very contagious.
H1N1流感传染性很强。
Alright, so you want to avoid contagious people but you might also want to avoid people who
好的，所以你想避开有传染性的人，但你可能也想避开那些有
have this next word.
下一个词的人。
It's called a rash.
它叫皮疹。
A rash, exactly.
皮疹，没错。
So why do you want to avoid people who have a rash?
那为什么要避开有皮疹的人呢？
They might have a contagious rash.
他们可能有传染性的皮疹。
Who knows but you can get a rash for a number of different reasons.
谁知道呢，但皮疹可能由多种原因引起。
A rash is just basically a part of your skin that becomes irritated or uncomfortable and
皮疹基本上就是皮肤上变得刺激或不舒服的一部分，
sometimes it turns red or pink.
有时会变红或变粉。
Exactly.
没错。
So, as you said, it happens for different reasons.
所以，就像你说的，它由不同原因引起。
Sometimes you maybe have bad seafood in your skin and you start to have rashes all over
有时你可能吃了不好的海鲜，然后全身开始起皮疹。
your body.
全身都是。
Other times you can touch some plants that are dangerous like poison ivy or poison oak.
其他时候，你可能碰到一些危险的植物，比如毒藤或毒橡树。
And then you get a big rash.
然后你就会起一大片皮疹。
And our last word for today is a little bit dramatic.
我们今天最后一个词有点夸张。
She called him a biohazard.
她称他为生物危害。
Biohazard.
生物危害。
Well, let's take a look at these words individually.
好，我们逐个来看这些词。
The first word bio comes from the word biology.
第一个词“bio”来自“biology”（生物学）。
So that's something that is alive.
所以它指的是有生命的东西。
An animal, a plant or a person.
动物、植物或人。
And hazard is something that is dangerous.
而“hazard”指的是危险的东西。
So a biohazard is a, well, something that's alive that's dangerous.
所以“biohazard”就是，嗯，有生命且危险的东西。
Right.
对。
Something that's dangerous towards a living person, right, or organism.
对活人或者生物体有危险的东西。
For example, you don't want to be near an area that has a lot of radiation.
比如，你不想靠近辐射很强的区域。
It's a biohazard.
那是生物危害。
Exactly.
没错。
Or some of these diseases like Ebola virus.
或者像埃博拉病毒这样的疾病。
These are very dangerous towards living things.
这些对生物非常危险。
And so biohazard is the name for it.
所以“biohazard”就是它的名称。
Exactly.
没错。
And usually there's a symbol, a very clear symbol that kind of looks like a triangle
通常有一个标志，一个非常清晰的标志，看起来有点像三角形，
and it's red.
而且是红色的。
And even in movies it's appeared, right?
甚至在电影里也出现过，对吧？
I think in that movie.
我想是在那部电影里。
Yeah.
嗯。
It's red or yellow.
它是红色或黄色的。
Yeah, sometimes.
嗯，有时候是。
All right.
好的。
So biohazard.
所以是“biohazard”。
I think we've taken a look at a lot of words.
我想我们已经看了很多词了。
So why don't we listen to this dialogue again?
那我们再听一遍这段对话吧。
Let's slow it down a little bit.
我们放慢一点速度。
See if we can understand a little bit more.
看看能不能多理解一些。
What's wrong with you?
你怎么了？
Why are you scratching so much?
你怎么挠得这么厉害？
I feel itchy.
我觉得痒。
I can't stand it anymore.
我受不了了。
I think I may be coming down with something.
我想我可能生病了。
I feel lightheaded and weak.
我觉得头晕无力。
Let me have a look.
让我看看。
Whoa.
哇。
Get away from me.
离我远点。
What's wrong?
怎么了？
I think you have the chicken pox.
我想你得了水痘。
You're contagious.
你会传染的。
Get away.
离我远点。
Don't breathe on me.
别对着我呼吸。
Maybe it's just a rash or an allergy.
也许只是皮疹或过敏。
We can't be sure until I see a doctor.
得等我看过医生才能确定。
Well, in the meantime, you are a biohazard.
好吧，在那之前，你就是个生物危害。
I didn't get it when I was a kid and I've heard that you can even die if you get it
我小时候没得过这个，而且我听说如果成年后得这个，
as an adult.
甚至会死。
Are you serious?
你是认真的吗？
You always blow things out of proportion.
你总是把事情夸大。
In any case, I think I'll go take an oatmeal bath.
不管怎样，我想我要去洗个燕麦浴。
Eww.
呃。
All right.
好了。
We're back.
我们回来了。
Why don't we take a look at Fluency Builder and start taking a look at all these phrases.
我们来看看“流利度构建器”，开始学习所有这些短语。
Fluency Builder.
流利度构建器。
Well, the first one is something that we often say when we're starting to feel ill.
第一个是我们开始感觉不舒服时常说的话。
This phrase is coming down with.
这个短语是“coming down with”。
So I could say, I think I'm coming down with a cold, for example.
所以我可以这样说，比如，我觉得我快感冒了。
So basically, you say, I'm coming down with something.
基本上，你会说，我好像要生病了。
So a cold or I think I'm coming down with the flu.
比如感冒，或者我觉得我快得流感了。
So you're saying that I think I'm getting ill?
所以你的意思是，我觉得我快生病了？
Exactly.
没错。
It means I'm just starting to feel sick.
意思是我刚开始感觉不舒服。
And so you could say, I've had a cold for a week.
所以你可以说，我感冒已经一周了。
You wouldn't use the phrase I'm coming down with in this situation.
在这种情况下你不会用“coming down with”这个短语。
You'd only use it when you're starting to feel sick.
你只在刚开始感觉不舒服时用它。
Very good.
很好。
So you could ask your boss, I think I'm coming down with the flu.
所以你可以对老板说，我觉得我快得流感了。
Can I go home early?
我能早点回家吗？
Right.
对。
And I think this is a very useful phrase.
我觉得这是个很有用的短语。
It's very natural to say.
说起来很自然。
So why don't we listen to a couple of other examples?
那我们再听几个其他例子吧。
Example one.
例子一。
Honey will you take my temperature?
亲爱的，你能帮我量体温吗？
I think I'm coming down with something.
我觉得我好像要生病了。
Example two.
例子二。
You must be coming down with a cold.
你一定是快感冒了。
Example three.
例子三。
Tommy came down with the flu.
Tommy得了流感。
All right.
好的。
So coming down with, coming down with the flu, coming down with a cough, etc.
所以“coming down with”，得了流感，得了咳嗽等等。
All right.
好的。
What's our next phrase?
我们下一个短语是什么？
Well, this one's great.
嗯，这个很棒。
It's a filler phrase.
这是一个填充短语。
So in the meantime.
所以是“in the meantime”。
In the meantime.
“In the meantime”。
So I could say, all right, I'm going to go cook dinner.
所以我可以这么说：好的，我要去做晚饭了。
In the meantime, Marco, can you please clear the table?
与此同时，Marco，你能把桌子收拾一下吗？
Okay.
好的。
So while you are cooking dinner, I am doing something else.
所以当你做晚饭的时候，我在做别的事情。
I'm cleaning the table.
我在擦桌子。
So two things happening at the same time.
所以两件事同时发生。
In the meantime.
“In the meantime”。
Very good.
非常好。
So it's a filler, you say.
所以你说它是一个填充词。
Because usually it follows another phrase.
因为它通常跟在另一个短语后面。
So I'm going to be doing this report for a while.
所以我要花一段时间做这份报告。
In the meantime, can you just wait here on the sofa, please?
与此同时，你能在沙发上等一下吗？
Okay.
好的。
Very good.
非常好。
So in the meantime.
所以是“in the meantime”。
So you're connecting two different actions, two different ideas.
所以你在连接两个不同的动作、两个不同的想法。
Exactly.
没错。
Very good.
非常好。
In the meantime.
“In the meantime”。
And what about our last phrase?
那我们最后一个短语呢？
All right.
好的。
There are some people who really like to do this.
有些人真的很喜欢这样做。
And I might be one of them.
我可能就是其中之一。
It's called to blow things out of proportion.
这叫做“把小事夸大”。
All right.
好的。
And you're going to hear this phrase a lot with native English speakers.
你会经常听到母语为英语的人说这个短语。
And so to blow things out of proportion, well, it pretty much means that you're exaggerating
所以“to blow things out of proportion”，基本上意思是你夸大其词，
or you're making a really big deal out of something that's not very serious.
或者你把一件不太严重的事情搞得很大。
So for example, if you come over to my house and you break a glass and I start freaking
比如，如果你来我家，打碎了一个杯子，然后我抓狂，
out and yelling at you because you broke my glass.
冲你大喊大叫，因为你打碎了我的杯子。
I say, Marco, you're blowing things out of proportion.
我会说：Marco，你把事情夸大了。
I'll just buy you a new one.
我给你买个新的就行了。
It's not that serious.
没那么严重。
All right.
好吧。
So don't exaggerate.
所以别夸张了。
Right.
对。
And you can say like this with siblings, spouses or bosses who react very seriously.
你可以这样对兄弟姐妹、配偶或反应很严肃的老板说。
So you can say, hey, stop.
所以你可以说，嘿，停下。
Stop yelling like you're blowing things out of proportion.
别大喊大叫，好像你在小题大做。
This is not a really big deal.
这真的不是什么大事。
Exactly.
没错。
All right.
好吧。
So blowing things out of proportion.
所以“小题大做”就是这个意思。
Let's not do that.
我们别那样做。
Let's listen to our dialogue for the last time and then we'll be back.
让我们最后听一遍对话，然后回来。
What's wrong with you?
你怎么了？
Why are you scratching so much?
你怎么挠得这么厉害？
I feel itchy.
我觉得痒。
I can't stand it anymore.
我受不了了。
I think I may be coming down with something.
我想我可能生病了。
I feel lightheaded and weak.
我觉得头晕无力。
Let me have a look.
让我看看。
Whoa, get away from me.
哇，离我远点。
What's wrong?
怎么了？
I think you have chicken pox.
我觉得你得了水痘。
You're contagious.
你会传染的。
Get away.
走开。
Don't breathe on me.
别对着我呼吸。
Maybe it's just a rash or an allergy.
可能只是皮疹或过敏。
We can't be sure until I see a doctor.
在看过医生之前我们不能确定。
Well, in the meantime, you're a biohazard.
嗯，在那之前，你就是个生物危害。
I didn't get it when I was a kid and I've heard that you can even die if you get it
我小时候没得过，而且我听说如果成年后得水痘，
as an adult.
甚至可能会死。
Are you serious?
你是认真的吗？
You always blow things out of proportion.
你总是小题大做。
In any case, I think I'll go take an oatmeal bath.
不管怎样，我想我去洗个燕麦浴。
Eww.
呃。
All right.
好吧。
So Catherine, have you ever had the chicken pox?
那么凯瑟琳，你得过水痘吗？
I did.
我得过。
I have very, very clear memories of when I was a child and I had the chicken pox because
我对自己小时候出水痘的记忆非常非常清晰，因为
I believe it was Thanksgiving and I was about four or five years old.
我记得那是在感恩节，我当时大概四五岁。
And I didn't have an appetite, so I was not hungry.
我没有胃口，所以不觉得饿。
And all I could do was itch and drink.
我唯一能做的就是挠痒和喝水。
And so I still have little scars like you mentioned from where I couldn't stop myself
所以就像你提到的，我身上还留着一些小疤痕，因为我忍不住
from scratching my little marks.
去抓那些小印记。
Right.
对。
And well, why does the little boy say that he's going to go take an oatmeal bath?
那么，那个小男孩为什么说他要去洗燕麦浴呢？
An oatmeal bath.
燕麦浴。
Okay.
好的。
Well, this is one of the home remedies, one of the home cures for the itchiness.
嗯，这是一种家庭疗法，一种缓解瘙痒的家庭偏方。
All right.
明白了。
So it doesn't make your chicken pox go away, but it does make your skin feel better because
所以它不会让水痘消失，但能让你的皮肤感觉好一些，因为
it's very calming and smooth.
它非常舒缓和平滑。
So you can have some creams or some lotions, but other people like to take an oatmeal bath.
所以你可以用一些药膏或乳液，但其他人喜欢洗燕麦浴。
Right.
对。
So then you're not itching anymore.
这样你就不再痒了。
Right.
对。
But it's gross because you're sitting in oatmeal.
但坐在燕麦里感觉挺恶心的。
It is kind of gross.
是有点恶心。
Have you had the chicken pox?
你得过水痘吗？
I didn't know because I couldn't remember.
我不知道，因为我记不清了。
So actually my brother had it recently, so I was afraid that I didn't get it, but I called
实际上我哥哥最近得了水痘，所以我担心自己没得过，但我打电话
my mom.
问了我妈妈。
She said I got it, so I'm good.
她说我得过，所以我没事。
You're safe.
你安全了。
Yeah.
是的。
So that's the thing, right?
所以就是这样，对吧？
You can only get it once.
你只会得一次。
You don't have a problem.
你没有问题。
Well, we're curious to know, have you had the chicken pox?
嗯，我们很好奇，你得过水痘吗？
And if you did, was it really itchy or were you a lucky one and it wasn't so bad?
如果得过，是不是特别痒，还是你幸运，没那么严重？
So let us know on our website, englishpod.com.
所以请在我们的网站 englishpod.com 上告诉我们。
Right.
对。
And if you ever had any other common childhood illnesses like the mumps or the measles, right,
如果你还得过其他常见的儿童疾病，比如腮腺炎或麻疹，对吧，
you can also tell us about that.
你也可以告诉我们。
So we'll see you guys there and until next time.
那我们就在那里见，下次再见。
Bye everyone.
大家再见。
Enter a culture in which a child lives above the parents by invoking a parenting image
进入一种文化，在这种文化中，孩子通过唤起自己童年的父母形象来凌驾于父母之上。
of their childhood.
他们童年的形象。
So the clan really started out by messing around with the cards they thought about
所以这个家族一开始就是通过摆弄那些他们想到的卡片起步的。